<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Posts on Max&#39;s blog</title>
    <link>https://maxthomas.github.io/blog/post/index.xml</link>
    <description>Recent content in Posts on Max&#39;s blog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 15:58:08 -0500</lastBuildDate>
    <atom:link href="https://maxthomas.github.io/blog/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    <item>
      <title>From CyanogenMod to LineageOS on an Honor 5x</title>
      <link>https://maxthomas.github.io/blog/post/cm-to-lineage-kiwi/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 11 Mar 2017 15:58:08 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maxthomas.github.io/blog/post/cm-to-lineage-kiwi/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;In case you hadn&amp;rsquo;t heard, the Android operating system
&lt;a href=&#34;http://lifehacker.com/cyanogenmod-is-dead-and-its-successor-is-lineage-os-1790554964&#34;&gt;CyanogenMod is no longer around&lt;/a&gt;.
I had been using CyanogenMod on both my phones (Nexus 5 and Honor 5X)
with great success: I&amp;rsquo;m a big fan of the project, even though
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/WhisperSystems/Signal-Android/issues/127#issuecomment-13447074&#34;&gt;at least one important person would contend it&amp;rsquo;s less secure&lt;/a&gt;
than stock Android, at least for the plebs. Like your parents.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Personally, I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen to flash CyanogenMod on my devices to avoid
some of the bloatware that comes packaged with Android phones upon purchase.
Not only that, but the Honor 5X must have been shipped with some
absolutely horrible software choices, because it was very sluggish,
even with at-the-time impressive hardware specs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided I&amp;rsquo;d take a crack at &amp;ldquo;upgrading&amp;rdquo; to LineageOS 14.1 from
CyanogenMod 13.1 on the Honor 5X, mostly because I was having trouble
maintaining a WiFi connection to a 2.4 GHz network, which
&lt;a href=&#34;https://review.lineageos.org/#/c/163842/&#34;&gt;may have been resolved in a nightly update&lt;/a&gt;.
I also figured that I&amp;rsquo;d have to update eventually, given the
absence of future CyanogenMod updates.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;These notes are here to help others who may undertake the same task.
For those following along, I&amp;rsquo;m using Arch Linux on my laptop, so
commands in terminal form represent things that were run on Linux.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;tldr&#34;&gt;TLDR&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Find your phone &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.lineageos.org/devices.html&#34;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If yours is also Honor 5X: keep reading. If not: hope the docs are correct
and follow them.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;kiwi-users&#34;&gt;Kiwi users&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Download the &lt;a href=&#34;https://download.lineageos.org/kiwi&#34;&gt;build you want&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If you want Google Play Store / Android goodies,
download &lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.lineageos.org/gapps.html&#34;&gt;OpenGApps&lt;/a&gt;.
Be sure to read what each version offers before choosing.
Kiwi uses &lt;code&gt;arm64&lt;/code&gt; so be sure to pick that.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Get &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; &lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Android#Android_Debug_Bridge_.28ADB.29&#34;&gt;installed and set up&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If needed: enable developer mode on phone:
&lt;code&gt;Settings&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;About&lt;/code&gt;, &lt;code&gt;Build version&lt;/code&gt; x 7 taps&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enable USB debugging, advanced restart options in developer options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Plug in phone via USB to machine with &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; on it&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Run these commands, noting possible file name differences:

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;adb push lineage-14.1-20170308-nightly-kiwi-signed.zip /sdcard/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;code&gt;adb push open_gapps-arm64-7.1-pico-20170311.zip /sdcard/&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reboot phone into recovery: hold power button, restart,
look for Recovery Mode in options&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Once &lt;code&gt;TWRP&lt;/code&gt; loads, go to Wipe, then &lt;strong&gt;individually&lt;/strong&gt;
check each option, and swipe to wipe. E.g., Dalvik then swipe,
cache then swipe, &amp;hellip; until finished.
&lt;strong&gt;WARNING&lt;/strong&gt;: you may want to save the contents of your microSD card,
so don&amp;rsquo;t wipe that if you do!&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Still in &lt;code&gt;TWRP&lt;/code&gt;, click install, queue up the LineageOS zip,
then if you downloaded GApps, the GApps zip.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Flash&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Reboot&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Win&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those interested in the journey, read on.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;downloading-the-appropriate-files&#34;&gt;Downloading the appropriate files&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was easy to find the right files on
the &lt;a href=&#34;http://lineageos.org/&#34;&gt;LineageOS site&lt;/a&gt;. I&amp;rsquo;m
using the kiwi device, which
&lt;a href=&#34;http://wiki.lineageos.org/kiwi_install.html&#34;&gt;has a nice guide&lt;/a&gt;
that walks a user through installation instructions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to download two files: the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://mirrorbits.lineageos.org/full/kiwi/20170308/lineage-14.1-20170308-nightly-kiwi-signed.zip&#34;&gt;update itself&lt;/a&gt;,
and &lt;a href=&#34;http://opengapps.org/?api=7.1&amp;amp;variant=pico&#34;&gt;Open GApps&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I chose the &lt;code&gt;pico&lt;/code&gt; version because I do want the app store, but I have
no interest in using &amp;ldquo;OK Google&amp;rdquo; nor unlock via face.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then used &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; to push these files to my phone&amp;rsquo;s &lt;code&gt;/sdcard/&lt;/code&gt; folder:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;adb push lineage-14.1-20170308-nightly-kiwi-signed.zip /sdcard/
adb push open_gapps-arm64-7.1-pico-20170311.zip /sdcard/
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For those without &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; set up but are running linux, the arch wiki
&lt;a href=&#34;https://wiki.archlinux.org/index.php/Android#Android_Debug_Bridge_.28ADB.29&#34;&gt;has a nice guide&lt;/a&gt;.
Those using other OSes may appreciate the info but need other software.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;backing-up&#34;&gt;Backing up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The first thing I did was back up all my data to my laptop.
I did this the &amp;ldquo;old fashioned way&amp;rdquo;, mounting the device
and simply &lt;code&gt;rsync&lt;/code&gt;ing files to my laptop&amp;rsquo;s hard disk.
I used &lt;code&gt;simple-mtpfs&lt;/code&gt; from &lt;a href=&#34;https://aur.archlinux.org/packages/simple-mtpfs/&#34;&gt;AUR&lt;/a&gt;.
All I had to do was enable file transfer mode in the USB options
on my phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then thought it&amp;rsquo;d be a good idea to take a more wholesome
backup, perhaps done via the phone itself. That&amp;rsquo;s where I hit
the first of many issues.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;device-encryption&#34;&gt;Device encryption&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As someone concerned about my privacy, I&amp;rsquo;ve chosen to encrypt my
device. If you have an Android phone and are not sure if your device
is encrypted, you may want to
&lt;a href=&#34;https://www.howtogeek.com/141953/how-to-encrypt-your-android-phone-and-why-you-might-want-to/&#34;&gt;get educated about it&lt;/a&gt;.
In the part of the world I&amp;rsquo;m currently in, phone theft is not uncommon
so it&amp;rsquo;s important the data on my device cannot be easily accessed by
potential thieves.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In CyanogenMod, it was very easy to encrypt the device. Unfortunately,
there seems to be no way to decrypt the device. Adding more annoying
issues, the &lt;a href=&#34;http://teamw.in/project/twrp2/&#34;&gt;recovery mod I&amp;rsquo;m using&lt;/a&gt;
doesn&amp;rsquo;t even prompt for an option to decrypt the device, and produces
several errors when attempting to access the encrypted partitions; this
makes sense as it can&amp;rsquo;t access them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That meant no possible way to back up the device without a micro SD
card (which somehow I decided against purchasing before leaving the US
- &lt;em&gt;yuuge&lt;/em&gt; mistake!) or a special cable that allows micro-SD to USB storage
transfers.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Not only that, it was impossible to even wipe the device due to the
protected partitions! I then decided to try my luck with sideloading
the device.  Looking back I should have probably upgraded the recovery
software to the latest version, but
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/TeamWin/Team-Win-Recovery-Project/issues/247&#34;&gt;a few issues&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/TeamWin/Team-Win-Recovery-Project/issues/333&#34;&gt;didn&amp;rsquo;t inspire confidence&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then decided to take a crack at sideloading the LineageOS update.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;sideloading-via-adb&#34;&gt;Sideloading via adb&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not an expert in &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; but apparently it is possible to
&amp;ldquo;side load&amp;rdquo; things into the phone using this method. I&amp;rsquo;m still
&lt;a href=&#34;http://twrp.me/faq/ADBSideload.html&#34;&gt;not exactly sure what that technically means&lt;/a&gt;,
but I foolishly convinced myself it was worth a try after reading a
few light-on-info blog posts.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It was easy enough to sideload the update:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;ll2 :: ~ » adb sideload lineage-14.1-20170308-nightly-kiwi-signed.zip
Total xfer: 1.00x
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was that all I needed to a slick new phone operating system?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course not. But I wanted to see if it&amp;rsquo;d work at all, so I eagerly rebooted
the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;com-android-phone-has-stopped-working&#34;&gt;com.android.phone has stopped working&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The phone began to restart, and after some churning, it even prompted
me for my encryption password. I was actually thinking that this turkey
would run right out of the box.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then it occurred to me that I had forgotten to sideload OpenGApps,
so I was quite pessimistic that actual apps would work - defeating
the point of having a &amp;ldquo;smart phone&amp;rdquo;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What I didn&amp;rsquo;t expect, however, was the &amp;ldquo;black screen of death&amp;rdquo;
that awaited me about 30 seconds after unencrypting the device.
After that, a cascade of processes stopped working, including
very important-sounding ones, like &lt;code&gt;com.android.phone&lt;/code&gt; and
the system UI (&lt;strong&gt;!&lt;/strong&gt;). Looks like I was not successful on my first pass.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At this point I realized I was going to be Having Fun, so I got a
snack and put on a playlist, because this was not going to be a
quick project.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;recovery-mode&#34;&gt;Recovery mode&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It took me awhile to figure out that booting into recovery mode on the
Honor 5X involves holding volume-UP and power (not down as the wiki
indicates).  After figuring that out, I figured I&amp;rsquo;d first try to
update the recovery mode software in case they enabled some feature to
decrypt the device during recovery.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;They have &lt;a href=&#34;https://twrp.me/devices/huaweihonor5x.html&#34;&gt;some instructions&lt;/a&gt;
which I followed. I chose to try to install via TWRP itself: look
towards the middle section of that page &lt;code&gt;TWRP Install&lt;/code&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I downloaded the
&lt;a href=&#34;https://dl.twrp.me/kiwi/twrp-3.1.0-0-kiwi.img&#34;&gt;latest version for my phone&lt;/a&gt;
and pushed it:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;max@ll2:~ $ adb push $HOME/Downloads/twrp-3.1.0-0-kiwi.img /sdcard/
[100%] /sdcard/twrp-3.1.0-0-kiwi.img
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Per their instructions: go into recovery, click install, select the
image, click the pushed image, select recovery, and flash. Reboot
the phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After doing this, you&amp;rsquo;ll be tempted to hold the recovery mode
keys, but don&amp;rsquo;t do that - it just results in a boot loop.
Letting go will take you right back to the newly updated
TWRP recovery screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;It looks like the software update didn&amp;rsquo;t help: I&amp;rsquo;m still stuck
with an encrypted partition and no way to unlock it, and
a currently unusable phone. Next up: try to sideload both
the update and OpenGApps:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class=&#34;language-shell&#34;&gt;max@ll2:~ $ adb sideload lineage-14.1-20170308-nightly-kiwi-signed.zip
Total xfer: 1.00x
max@ll2:~ $ adb sideload Downloads/open_gapps-arm64-7.1-pico-20170311.zip
Total xfer: 1.43x
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Side note: the percentages for &lt;code&gt;adb&lt;/code&gt; don&amp;rsquo;t seem to match the progress
bar on TWRP&amp;rsquo;s screen. I know progress bars are often just made up
graphics to reassure users that &amp;ldquo;stuff is working&amp;rdquo; but that&amp;rsquo;s a little
sketchy.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Anyway, more importantly, things seemed to work, other than
the inability to access &lt;code&gt;/data&lt;/code&gt; - presumably due to encryption.
That doesn&amp;rsquo;t seem ideal.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Will it blend?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;progress&#34;&gt;Progress?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;After rebooting, I now got to see my beautiful phone&amp;rsquo;s home
screen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For about a second.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then, the warnings about apps closing started appearing, and
everything went black&amp;hellip; again.  Hardly ideal. I decided to reboot
into recovery, which is about the only thing I&amp;rsquo;ve figured out how to
do reliably at this stage.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But wait: when I try to boot into recovery, I&amp;rsquo;m now prompted by a Huawei
eRecovery software splash screen. The hell? Did sideloading both apps somehow
annihilate TWRP? Or did the recovery mode keys change yet again?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was somewhat tempted to give up, plow ahead with the Huawei software,
then just nuke everything once it had - hopefully - restored my phone to
&lt;em&gt;Working Condition&lt;/em&gt;. At least it was an option. But I figured I&amp;rsquo;d try to
at least get TWRP to show up before folding.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Finally, I was able to get TWRP to show up by holding volume-UP and
power during the duration of the boot until TWRP shows up. Letting go
prematurely somehow invokes the Huawei recovery utility. Perhaps that
will be useful info.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;rsquo;s try once more with TWRP to get something going.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;act-with-intent&#34;&gt;Act with intent&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I decided to use TWRP to, individually, wipe everything, but instead
of checking all the boxes at once, check them individually. In other words:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click wipe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click advanced wipe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select Dalvik / ART &lt;code&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; Swipe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select cache &lt;code&gt;=&amp;gt;&lt;/code&gt; Swipe&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Repeat for everything related to the phone - except maybe MicroSD card if you
value its contents&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my surprise, this actually worked. There were no issues, except an
odd error about an invalid .zip file when the wiping Dalvik.  I&amp;rsquo;m not
sure how or why it worked. But now I was very optimistic that I would
be able to normally install LineageOS and OpenGApps per the original
instructions, and hopefully, end up with a usable phone.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had to repush them as I had wiped internal storage, using the same
&lt;code&gt;adb push&lt;/code&gt; commands from earlier.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I then clicked Install, selected the lineage zip, then added the open
gapps zip to the queue. Somewhat eerily, the process failed when I checked
zip file verification. So I unchecked it, queued up both zips again,
waited, &amp;hellip; and hoped.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;boom-outta-here&#34;&gt;Boom - outta here&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And just like that, after some serious loading, I was greeted by a
setup screen much like the first time I put CyanogenMod on the device.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I finally have got a LineageOS enabled phone with OpenGApps pico.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;wrapping-up&#34;&gt;Wrapping up&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well, as one should expect with any major software transition,
switching things around wasn&amp;rsquo;t the smoothest experience. But with a
little patience, some music, a cup of decaf coffee with a hint of soy
milk, and the Internet, I was able to upgrade to LineageOS - leaving
CyanogenMod behind for good.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ll be forking and contributing the LineageOS wiki with things
that I found that may help others. Here&amp;rsquo;s hoping the process
is not as cumbersome as the software update was.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Now Entering an Analytics-Free Zone</title>
      <link>https://maxthomas.github.io/blog/post/analytics-free/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 19 Feb 2017 17:47:31 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maxthomas.github.io/blog/post/analytics-free/</guid>
      <description>

&lt;p&gt;Telling people you are starting a blog is one of those things that
typically garners a reaction. Mostly, it involves questions: what will you
discuss?  How often will you post? Are you going to quit before you start
(poignant!)?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Occasionally, however, you&amp;rsquo;ll also get advice on what to discuss, how
often to post, and many other things. I&amp;rsquo;m always grateful to learn from
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wiktionary.org/wiki/everyone&#34;&gt;people who have blogged more than me&lt;/a&gt;,
so naturally I was excited to hear about others&amp;rsquo; blogging experiences.
Some people even showed me their blogs.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At least two friends, whom I would consider non-technical, offered to
show me their Wordpress setup, complete with statistics about which
users from what countries had visited their site, what pages had been
the most popular, and so forth. I believe this functionality is
offered by WP out of the box as an analytics package.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;m not sure if they knew, but they also had Google Analytics (GA) set
up on their sites. I wasn&amp;rsquo;t sure if GA was powering Wordpress or was
an independent thing. In any event, data was being collected via the
ever-present web analytics on the sites.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-brief-primer-on-web-analytics&#34;&gt;A brief primer on web analytics&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_analytics&#34;&gt;Web analytics&lt;/a&gt; essentially
involve tracking data generated by interacting with a web site. Much
of this data is associated with a user&amp;rsquo;s behavior - how they got to
the site, how much time they spent on a page, whether or not the next
page they went to was on the same domain, how long pages are loading on average,
what city and country visitors are coming from, and other related measurements.
Wordpress, Google Analytics and others provide useful aggregations of
this data and expose this data to the owner of the particular blog or
web site.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Generally speaking, this data can be very useful for improving the
website. There&amp;rsquo;s certainly utility in knowing, for example, the most
popular referrers (perhaps there&amp;rsquo;s strategy to develop there when it
comes to ad placement or identifying an audience), the most popular
articles, the percentage of your audience who can afford to spend
money on what you&amp;rsquo;re selling, and so forth.  I believe there are even
some social media components: for example, number of users coming from
the &amp;lsquo;book and Twitter.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Of course, if all the numbers read 0, you&amp;rsquo;ve got some work to do. But
don&amp;rsquo;t fret about that too much.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I can see how this data is both useful and fun to look at, for
non-technical people as well as those of us who work with and make
decisions based off data on a daily basis. There&amp;rsquo;s a certain positive
reaction, according to my friend, when a new visitor from Bolivia
stumbles upon one of his articles about India (I didn&amp;rsquo;t have the heart
to explain that it may just be a bunch of
&lt;a href=&#34;https://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Internet_bot&#34;&gt;bots&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I imagine the insights are even more relevant if your blog is at a
point where significant traffic is driving referrals, products, or ad
revenue - in other words, the money you get to take home. Pretty cool,
huh?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;it-s-just-a-numbers-game&#34;&gt;It&amp;rsquo;s just a numbers game&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;But the data must come from somewhere, and in this case, it&amp;rsquo;s almost
certainly from users unaware of, or unable to stop, the
tracking. There&amp;rsquo;s no information, opt-out process, or any other
indication that the users&amp;rsquo; mouse clicks, location, and next site
visited are being tracked.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Many users that are not tech savvy probably can&amp;rsquo;t even
identify what web analytics are capable of, much less identify sites
(hint: &lt;em&gt;virtually all&lt;/em&gt;) that use them. It&amp;rsquo;s not possible to know if you&amp;rsquo;re
on a Google Analytics site until it&amp;rsquo;s too late - when GA has already
loaded and presumably sent data back - without your consent.  And, as
far as I can tell, Google Analytics
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.outfox.com/do-not-track-for-google-analytics/&#34;&gt;does not respect do-not-track&lt;/a&gt;,
which is already a somewhat technical feature.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;More advanced users can
&lt;a href=&#34;https://disconnect.me/&#34;&gt;protect themselves to some extent&lt;/a&gt;.
Or, if you truly trust Google, you can install some plugin that
&lt;em&gt;allegedly&lt;/em&gt; tells Google Analytics not to send data back when visiting
sites with GA. I won&amp;rsquo;t link to this as I don&amp;rsquo;t want to appear to
encourage users to download this archive without seeing its contents,
and I&amp;rsquo;m certainly not volunteering to scope it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&#34;piwik-the-savior&#34;&gt;Piwik, the savior?&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Before you think I&amp;rsquo;m putting Google on blast unfairly, I won&amp;rsquo;t
spare &lt;a href=&#34;https://piwik.org/&#34;&gt;other analytics software&lt;/a&gt; either. While I
appreciate some of their sales points - owning the data, &amp;ldquo;user privacy
protection&amp;rdquo;, F/OSS - at the end of the day, it is exposing collection
of user data that, generally, the users aren&amp;rsquo;t aware of.  Lastly, it
involves standing up MySQL (in 2017?) and PHP (?!)  thus
requiring a running server, not to mention exposing a plethora of
potential security issues.  The average web site owner has absolutely
no chance of fulfilling the advertised user privacy protection when
faced with administering a PHP-MySQL stack on their own.
&lt;a href=&#34;https://github.com/piwik/piwik/issues/500&#34;&gt;Postgres is not even supported&lt;/a&gt;,
and given that issue has been open for 8 years now, probably won&amp;rsquo;t be.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;back-to-user-space&#34;&gt;Back to user space&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Needless to say, the user gets the raw end of this deal. At minimum,
they&amp;rsquo;re blissfully unaware of the massive amounts of data they leave
behind when visiting web sites, how they are tracked leaving and
entering other sites, and so forth.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I will focus on these issues in more (and less, for those who don&amp;rsquo;t
work in tech) detail in upcoming articles, but for now, it&amp;rsquo;s
sufficient to say that it&amp;rsquo;s completely unacceptable to do this to
users here. As someone interested primarily in &lt;strong&gt;helping&lt;/strong&gt; users, as
well as maintaining and protecting privacy, this sort of hidden data
collection is not very attractive.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;a-matter-of-principles&#34;&gt;A matter of principles&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I won&amp;rsquo;t be adding or using analytics to this blog, no
matter how useful they may be to developing it. To be
honest, it&amp;rsquo;s a principled (and therefore simple) decision: as someone
whose intent is to help users as well as someone who values privacy and
has put in effort into not being tracked online, I can&amp;rsquo;t possibly
consider using privacy-compromising technology here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;At first, I thought this might be somewhat of a Stallman-esq stance:
this blog would be the only site, or one of a few, that chose not to
embed analytics or social media &lt;del&gt;trackers&lt;/del&gt; buttons. Many would claim:
what&amp;rsquo;s the point? Join in on the massive vacuuming of your users&amp;rsquo; data
for your benefit (as well as the benefit of a large advertising company)!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To my delight, this had been done by a couple of other blogs I had
seen recently.  &lt;a href=&#34;https://michael-myers.github.io/blog/&#34;&gt;Mike&amp;rsquo;s blog&lt;/a&gt;,
from which I essentially
&lt;a href=&#34;http://www.urbandictionary.com/define.php?term=Tax&amp;amp;defid=56623&#34;&gt;taxed&lt;/a&gt;
the entire setup of my own blog, has chosen to omit both GA as well as
Facebook and Twitter buttons on his site. He also went to the trouble
of removing GA from the otherwise excellent
&lt;a href=&#34;http://themes.gohugo.io/purehugo/&#34;&gt;purehugo&lt;/a&gt; theme,
contributions which I gratefully used myself. He justifies not using
analytics with a privacy argument.
&lt;a href=&#34;http://jacquesmattheij.com/the-fastest-blog-in-the-world&#34;&gt;Another blog&lt;/a&gt;
takes a different but also principled approach, reducing cruft and
inefficiency and discussion about how it these things reflect the
state of our society in general.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I personally appreciate both positions, but the privacy one rings
closer to home.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&#34;core-purposes-as-guidance&#34;&gt;Core purposes as guidance&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;One theme I want to be a part of this blog is the idea of helping
others navigate a world in which data they emit is frequently
collected, sold, bought, stolen, and battled over in courts, both
normal and secret (among other things).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;While I have some goals for the blog, I can&amp;rsquo;t share the specifics due to
&lt;a href=&#34;http://berkeleysciencereview.com/when-telling-others-about-your-goals-compromises-them/&#34;&gt;psychological reasons&lt;/a&gt;.
None of the goals, however, involve monetizing users. As a result, web
analytics won&amp;rsquo;t be a part of the experience around here.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;With that said, enjoy a non-intrusive (and hopefully speedy)
experience on this blog, now and in to the future.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>first</title>
      <link>https://maxthomas.github.io/blog/post/firstPost/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2017 22:42:46 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://maxthomas.github.io/blog/post/firstPost/</guid>
      <description>&lt;p&gt;Welcome to my blog. I&amp;rsquo;m told that perfection is the enemy of the
good - or something like that - so I&amp;rsquo;m getting on with starting this
blog up&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&amp;hellip; just as soon as I choose a theme&amp;hellip;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As I see it, this blog will contain topics related to technology,
software, security and privacy, and may be a little bit of financial
and business information. That sounded super dry, but hopefully
we&amp;rsquo;ll have a bit of fun along the way.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I&amp;rsquo;ve done a ton of work that has never seen the light of day. I hope
this blog will be a way for me to give a little something back to the
community.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Thanks for reading.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>